Register of the Boris Aleksandrovich Kriukov Papers, 1917-1923
Hoover Institution Archives
Boris Aleksandrovich Kriukov Papers,
1917-1923
34002
Kriukov, Boris Aleksandrovich, 1898-1983
4 manuscript boxes, 9 envelopes (2.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoranda; military and naval intelligence reports; civil, naval, and military orders; correspondence; and photographs, relating to the Russian Revolution and Civil War in the Siberian Far East, especially operations of the Amur Flotilla (Red) and the Siberian Flotilla (White)
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1934.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Gajda, R. (Rudolf); Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920) Armiëiìa; Far Eastern Region (Siberia)--History; Primorskaëiìa oblast' (Russia); Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution 1917-1921; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Naval operations
Biographical Note
1898, July 20 Born, Minousinsk, Siberia
1917 Graduated form the Alexander Military Academy, Moscow
1917 Served in 95th Infantry Regiment
1918 Served in the 2nd Kazan Infantry Regiment
1918-1920 Served in the Marine Corps under Admiral Kolchak
1921-1923 Served in the Siberian Flotilla
1928 Graduted from New York State College of Forestry, Syracuse University and entered the service of the Intercontinental Rubber Company
1930 Appointed as consulting forester for the Insular Lumber Company
1931 Entered the service of the United States Rubber Company
Series Description
- Subject File, 1917-1923. (Boxes 1-4)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, lists, charts, notes, printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Miscellaneous, 1917-1923. (Box 4)
  Clippings, typewritten and handwritten notes. Includes summary of Kriukov collection by Elena Varneck.
- Photographs, 1921-1924., (294 prints / 10 negatives / 9 envelopes (Box 34002 - 8.21)
Container List
- Subject File, 1917-1923
  - Amur River Flotilla (Box 1.)
    - Siberian Flotilla, Chief of Operations Section, telegram and letter to, 1921-1922
    - Siberian Flotilla, Chief of Operations Section, telegram from
    - Siberian Flotilla, Commander of, reports to, 1921-1922
    - Semenov, Ataman, report to, February 1921
  - Belorussia
  - Bolshevik Organizational Activities in the Far East, 1921-1922
  - Bolshevik propaganda
  - Coding and decoding (compiled by A. Semenov's staff), 1921
  - Communist Party in the Soviet Union
  - Communist Party (R.S.F.S.R.), membership card and labour card, 1920-1921
  - Currency
    - Blagoveshchensk, 1920
    - Caucasus and Southern Russia
    - Chita
    - Far Eastern Republic, 1920
    - Far Eastern Republics, miscellaneous (Transbaikal, Priamur, etc.), 1920-1922
    - Nikolaevsk (on the Amur), 1920
    - Petrograd Provisional Government, 1917
    - R.S.F.S.R., 1920
    - Siberian Provisional Government, Omsk, 1918-1920
  - Diary of a wife of a partisan, 1919
  - Gaida, General R. I. Materials relating to Gaida's rebellion in Vladivostok, November 1919
  - Germany
  - Kamchatka (Petropavlovsk)
  - Kamenev, L., "Istoriia partii kommunistov v Rossii i V.I. Lenin," 1920
  - Kappel Army, military chiefs of
  - "Krasnoe Znamia", organ of the Maritime Province Russian Communist Party. 1922 - #8, 11-13, 18-20
  - Maritime Province
    - Communist Party
    - Novo-Tadushinsky Rural Society, 1921
    - Political situation, 1921-1922
  - Military units
  - Naval Border Guard Section. Journal of secret service information, Vladivostok, June -August, 1922 (Box 2.)
  - Naval Ministry at Omsk, 1919
  - Olga (town of)
    - "Bor'ba" (partisan newsletter), 1921
    - Military units in, 1921
    - Partisan detachments near, Orders, 1921
  - Omsk
    - Office of the 2nd Quartermaster General, 1919
    - Office of the Supreme Ruler, 1919
    - Stenographic account of negotiations for the surrender of Omsk Government to the Political Center, Irkutsk, 1920
  - Priamur Government, Army
  - Priamur Provisional Government
    - Leaflets
    - Military forces
    - Ministry of the Interior, Administrative Section, 1921-1922
    - Orders
    - Reports, of the Commander of Troops, to Commander of Siberian Flotilla, December 1921 -October 1922
    - Summaries of Operations of military forces from staff of the Commander-in-Chief, September 1921 -October 1922
    - Summaries of Operations of military forces (by the staff of Siberian Flotilla), December 1921 -October 1922 (Box 3.)
  - Priamur Zemsky Sobor, July 23 -August 6, 1922
  - Red Navy, 1920
  - Russian Emigres in Europe, 1921-1922
  - Russian-Asiatic Unified Society
  - Semenov, Ataman. "Memorandum to the Peoples of the World," 1921
  - Siberian Flotilla
    - Application for service
    - Cruise of "Ilia Muromets," August -October 1922
    - Cruise of "Lieutenant Dydymov," June 1922
    - Cruise of training ship "Patrokl'," November 1922
    - Evacuation from Vladivostok to Philippines, October 24, 1922
    - Materials prior to May 26, 1921 (overthrow of Bolsheviks)
    - Miscellaneous
    - Orders of the Commander, 1921-1923
    - Radio Information Summary, September 1, 1922
    - Report of the Commander
    - Reports from Commanders of ships along the coast, 1922
    - Reports of Head of Counter-Intelligence to Commander, 1921
    - "Russkii Listok" (newsletter of the Siberian Flotilla in the Philippines), 1923 - #5-8 (April - May)
    - Summaries of Operations of the Staff of the Commander, April -October 1922
    - Tactical Order to the Commander, April 7, 1922
    - Telegrams, intercepted from the Bolsheviks
    - War-Navy Department, orders, 1921
    - "Ways to Regenerate the Russian Navy"
  - Soloviev, E. P., Treatise in memory of fallen soldiers of World War I and the Russian Revolution
  - Soviet Russia. "Summary of Information on the Situation in Soviet Russia"
  - Soviet Union, 1921-1922 (Box 4.)
  - Yakutsk Province, 1922
  - Vladivostok
    - Materials prior to May 26, 1921
    - Orders to the garrison of the fortress and city, April 1922 -October 1922
- Miscellaneous
  - Clippings (Box 4.)
    - Vladivostok newspapers, 1921-1922
  - Miscellaneous
  - Summary of Kriukov Collection by Elena Varneck
- Photographs
  - 117 prints of the Siberian Flotilla stationed at Olongapo, Philippine Isles., March 1923-June 1924 (Folder A)
  - 23 prints of the Siberian Flotilla cruise to the Philippines.>October 24, 1922 - February 1, 1923. 61 prints, 5 negatives, of Siberian Flotilla stationed in Vladivostok, 1921-1922. (Folder B)
    Included are photos of R/A Stark, General Diterikhs and R/A Bezuarg.
  - 36 prints of Siberian Flotilla cruise from Vladivostok to Petropavlovsk, Kamchatka., July - November 1922 (Folder C)
  - 7 prints, 1 negative, of funeral of Col. Gludkin and Capt. Garkovenko in Vladivostok and 1 print of Gen. Gaida., undated (Folder D)
  - 16 prints, 2 negatives, of the Primaur Government Army., 1921-22 (Folder E)
  - 10 prints, 1 negative of the Zemsky Sobor, Vladivostok., July 23 - Aug. 6, 1922 (Folder F)
  - 9 prints of the city of Vladivostok, 1919-1922 (Folder G)
  - 15 prints dealing with White Russians in Vladivostok and the Far East., 1919-1923 (Folder H)
  - 1 8x10 negative of a group of ship and its' passengers and crew., circa 1922 (Folder I)